Davis and Geck Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Davis and Geck Company Records.
undated, 1909-1997.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Davis and Geck Company.
14.5 linear feet.
MSS19980297
The Davis and Geck Company was founded in 1909 by Charles T. Davis and Fred A. Geck. The company specialized in surgical sutures, beginning with catgut and moving on to kangaroo tendons and later to advanced synthetic materials. For much of its history, Davis and Geck was the world's second largest producer of surgical sutures. The company became part of American Cyanamid in 1930. After subsequent sales, the company was renamed Sherwood, Davis and Geck. Though the D+G offices were initially located in Brooklyn, N.Y., the company purchased a factory in Danbury, Conn., in the early 1950s. This factory was scheduled for closure in 1998 following the sale of Sherwood, Davis and Geck to the Tyco Corporation and the transfer of plant operations to Mexico.
History
The Davis and Geck Company was founded in 1909 by Charles T. Davis and Fred A. Geck. Geck was experienced in the marketing of sutures from his experience with another company, Van Horn and Sawtell. Charles Davis already owned his own medical supply company. The company's two other founders were Frank C. Bradeen, Vice President, and Benjamin F. Hirsch, as secretary. After only a few months, Fred Geck withdrew from the company as he did not have the requisite knowledge to assist in suture manufacture. Bradeen left the company after only two years. Benjamin Hirsch remained with the company up until the 1950s, and was responsible for much of the company's marketing strategy and for securing several patents. It should be noted that the company's first production facility was in the back room of a livery stable located on Carleton Avenue in Brooklyn, NY.
In 1909, the year that the Davis and Geck Company was founded, most hospitals were sterilizing their own catgut sutures, frequently through the use of a chemical solution. The process was imperfect, and frequently resulted in infections or operative delays. In 1913 the Davis and Geck Company introduced the Calustro-thermal process for the heat sterilization of suture tubes after the sutures were sealed inside. This provided hospitals with a reliable product, and saved time in the operating room as well.
The Davis and Geck Company was extremely busy filling contracts during the first World War. In 1922, Davis and Geck began to market Atraumatic needles, which were eyeless needles that had the sutures directly attached to the needle. However, by this time the founder of the company had become involved in a murder investigation. On 17 February 1921, Charles T. Davis shot and killed a police detective who had come to his office to clarify an insurance claim filed by Davis. Davis' mental health came into question - apparently he was convinced that Kaiser Wilhelm was trying to assassinate him. Davis was confined to a mental institution for a few years, but faced a formal criminal trial in 1925 after his mental state had considerably improved. He was found guilty and sentenced to 10-20 years in prison.
By 1930, with Charles T. Davis scheduled for a parole hearing, a battle was brewing for control of the company between Davis and his wife. Mrs. Davis claimed to have improved the company during her husband's incarceration, and had also installed her paramour, a Polish nobleman named Cornelius Tuczynski, as vice president of the company. The Davises settled the ownership dispute by selling Davis and Geck to the American Cyanamid Corporation for three million dollars.
Beginning in 1928, the Davis and Geck Company also began to produce surgical films as a way to document new procedures and to assist in the training of doctors and nurses. This program continued into the 1980s as the Cliné Clinic Films Program. The company also gained prestige from 1927 through 1950 through a series of dramtic print advertisements entitled “Sutures in Ancient Surgery,” all of which featured prints by noted artist and photographer Lejaren à Hiller. The original photos from this series have been donated to the Art Institute of Chicago.
Nylon sutures were introduced in 1941. Just prior to Word War II, Davis and Geck held appproximately 70% of the domestic market for sutures, and during the war provided 75% of the sutures required by the U.S. military. However, after the war the company began to lose market share to Ethicon, a division of Johnson and Johnson. Failure to respond to improved packaging introduced by Ethicon led to a reduced market share of 40% by 1952.
In 1951, Davis and Geck acquired a factory in Danbury, Connecticut, formerly owned by the Mutual Rough Hat Company. Production began at this plant in 1953, and it remained the company's primary production facility up until the 1990s. At its peak, over 2000 different surgical products were produced at this one location. Towards the latter 1950s, Cyanamid chose to drop the Davis and Geck name, renaming the company as the Surgical Products Division of American Cyanamid, though retaining the D&G trademark. The Davis and Geck name resurfaced by the 1970s, by which time the company had introduced sutures based on an organic material called polyglycolic acid. These sutures were strong and easy to tie in knots, but could also be completely absorbed by the body's own tissue over time. This generation of sutures provided the backbone for the company's renewed presence in the global marketplace, continuing to the present day.
By the middle 1990s, Davis and Geck was no longer a subsidiary of American Cyanamid. The company was known as Sherwood, Davis and Geck through 1997. The Danbury factory was scheduled for closure in 1998 following the sale of Sherwood, Davis and Geck to the Tyco Corporation and the transfer of plant operations to Mexico.
(The above history was compiled through the use of documents found in the collection, including accounts written by Ben Hirsch and Charles Riall.)
Scope and Content
Collection highlights include several typescript histories of the company prepared at various times by members of the Davis and Geck administration, including Ben Hirsch and Charles T. Riall. Other materials include promotional literature describing Davis and Geck products from the 1910s through the 1980s. Some intra-company literature is also present, including newsletters, customer service guidelines, and a plant supervisor's manual. The map case contains floorplans of the Danbury factory, detailing a proposed 1995 renovation. Artifacts obtained from the factory have been donated to the Menczer Museum of Medecine and Dentistry in Hartford, Conn. The Eli Whitney Museum has also received materials from the Davis and Geck plant.
Materials have been placed in a rough order that puts historical documents first, followed by advertisements and product literature, and moving on to company publications and Cyanamid annual reports.
Arrangement
Series I: Records ( undated, 1909-1997 ) includes all the materials in the collection.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Medical supplies industry--United States.; Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Sutures.; Danbury (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Sutures.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Photographs.; Floor Plans.; Memorabilia.; Administrative Records.; Slides.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials donated by Davis and Geck and Charles T. Riall in June 1998. The patent materials were donated in 2008 by the Hartford Medical Society, which also holds Davis and Geck Company materials.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Records, undated, 1909-1997
  - Correspondence from Charles T. Riall to Ian Lawson, circa 1997 (Box 1)
  - Three typed manuscripts - overview of Davis and Geck history, circa 1972-1979
  - Davis and Geck historical articles, 1953-1986
  - Historical articles in bound folder, 1989
  - Miscellaneous historical documents, 1951-1992
  - “The Science of Bow-Strings,” historical manuscript, 1953
  - Documents relating to trial of Charles T. Davis, 1921-1930, 1986
  - Manuscript drafts of historical articles by Charles T. Riall, circa 1985
  - Drafts of Davis and Geck biography for Danbury historical book, 1984-1986
  - Davis and Geck Patent Records, 1934-1965
  - Customer complaint form and special products order form, 1984-1985
  - 'Literature of D+G Sutures' folder cover, undated
  - Davis and Geck Publications - 3 pamphlets, circa 1916-1923
  - Davis and Geck Publications - 6 pamphlets, circa 1916-1929
  - Davis and Geck Publications - 5 pamphlets, circa 1913-1929
  - Davis and Geck Publications - 4 pamphlets, circa 1920-23
  - Print advertisements (photocopies), 1913-1922
  - Print advertisements, 1931-1935
  - Documents pertaining to L. Hiller and the “Sutures in Ancient Surgery” photo series, 1927-1997
  - Ordering info. and price lists - U.S., Canada, and England, 1937-1949
  - Cyanamid Surgical Products Direct-Purchase Plan, circa 1958
  - Patent materials, 1953, 1957-1958
  - Promotional materials (9 items), 1957-1989
  - Promotional materials not related to products (7 items), 1927, 1970, 1989
  - Publications: Lifelines and Diamond Glitters (9 items), 1953-1968, 1984
  - Publication: 'Strings and Things' (1 item), 1978
  - Cyanamid UK supplier's manual, circa 1990
  - American Cyanamid Annual Reports (4 items), 1957-1969
  - American Cyanamid Annual Reports (4 items), 1974-1978
  - American Cyanamid Annual Reports (3 items), 1980-1987
  - American Cyanamid Annual Reports (3 items), 1988-1993
  - Sherwood Davis and Geck Service Awards (1 item), 1997
  - Memorabilia (D&G logos, 4 items), circa 1970s? (Box 2)
  - 'Initial Sales Training' folder, 1989
  - 'Needle Plant Prospectus' folder, 1982
  - 'Supervisor's Manual - Danbury Plant' folder, 1958-1977
  - Product catalog folder, 1976-1977
  - Product catalog folder, 1986-1987
  - Package of lecture slides belonging to Dr. Lawson, 1998?
  - Publications--Diamond Glimmers and LifeLines [incomplete], 1959-1985
  - "Primary Nursing Care Workshop," featuring Dr. Joan O'Leary, undated
  - Gold Cup (permanent file), 1975, 1977
  - Clippings, undated
  - 5 promotional posters, mounted on styrofoam backing, circa 1980s? (Box 3)
  - 3 safety award plaques, 1957, 1980, 1987
  - 1 lab coat with company logo, undated
  - Research & Development award (Silver bowl), undated (Box 4)
  - Thermal mug, 1994
  - Water bottle, 1991
  - Highlighters, Buttons, pins and related promotional materials, undated
  - Coverlet® adhesive dressing (1 box), undated
  - Trivia questionnaire, undated
  - Text for slide show, 1989
  - Davis and Geck tie, circa 1980
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
  - Slides, undated
  - Movie film (surgeon using D&G products), undated
  - Audio Cassette (training tape), circa 1994
  - 16mm film of James Affleck, CEO of American Cyanamid entitled, "Changes and Challenges", circa 1970 (Box 6)
  - Album of an open house, 1980
  - Life Lines, 1989-1995
  - Safety data sheets, 1980
  - Written materials concerning manufacturing processes, undated
  - Correspondence to and from the war department, 1917-1918
  - Instruction manual and telephone directory, 1994
  - Atraumatic needles, undated
  - 6 slides, undated
  - ID badge of Dr. Ian Lawson, 1987
  - Photo of 'Joe' Judy, undated
  - 2 rolls of film, undated
  - Make up kit, undated
  - Framed memorandum recording the absorption of polglycolic ester (PGA) in laboratory animals, 1963 (Box AS)
  - 'Commitment to Danbury' floor plans (4 items), 1995 (Box OS)
  - Photo enlargements of D&G products (4 items), 1985
  - 'Sutures in Ancient Surgery' prints - 2 items, plus `Best Wishes Class of 1959' - photo of Danbury factory (1 item), 1928-1930, 1959
  - 2 photos - picture of a livery stable, and photo of site of former D&G offices in Manhattan, 1983
  - Photo enlargements of D&G products (2 items), undated
  - Safety certificates (3 items), 1962, 1981, 1987
  - Enlargement of company roster photo, circa 1920s
  - Folder containing oversized photocopies of safety awards and patent certificates, undated
  - Safety Award placques, 1965, 1969, 1981, 1984